<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The charge of the court baron</title>
            <author>Southwark (London, England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101707</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837515</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837515</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1841</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12620)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1841)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1009:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The charge of the court baron</title>
                  <author>Southwark (London, England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ihon Cawood, prynter to the Quenes Maiestie. Cum priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>. Anno.M.D.LXI. [1561]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Probably issued with "The articles of lete and court for the lyberties of Southwarke", 1561--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B¹.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; trimmed at head, affecting running title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Courts baron and courts leet --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1841:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1841:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶THE Charge of the <hi>Court Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Ihon <hi>Cawood, Prynter to the Quenes Maieſtie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="privilege">
                        <p>Cum Priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Anno. M.D.LXI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="charge">
            <pb facs="tcp:1841:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1841:2"/>
            <head>The Charge of the Court Baron.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Yrſte ye good men that be ſworn, ye ſhal inquire and truely preſent al the ſuters that owe any ſute vnto this court at thys day, for there tenures yf they be here or noo, and preſente there names, that make default.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf there be anye tenaunte dede, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the laſt lawe day, ye ſhal inquire of him, and do vs to wete, what he held of this lordeſhyp, at the day of hys death, and what aduauntage the Lorde ſhoulde haue by hys death, as warde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryage, reliefe fine, or eſtchete, or anye other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytte, and who is hys nexte heyre, and what age he is of and in whoſe kepynge.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf there be anye rente, cuſtome, or ſeruyce wythdrawen from thys Lordeſhyppe, that ought of ryght to be done, ye ſhal inquyre by whome it is withdrawen, and what cuſtome or ſeruyce it is, and in what Baylyffes tyme, and howe longe it hathe bene wythholdenne. And where the lande lyeth that we maye dyſtrayne for the arrerages that are behynde.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf there be anye bonde of bloude, that putteth hys ſonne to ſcoole, to make hym a prieſt, or a prentyſe, or ſetteth hym
<pb facs="tcp:1841:3"/>
to crafte or maryeth hys daughter without leue, ye ſhal do vs to wytte.</p>
            <p>Alſo if there be any bond man that let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth hys land for the halfe, or for the thyrd ſheafe, without leaue, or ells yf there be any bonde man that with draweth his goodes, or cattells, out of thys lordeſhyppe without leue ye ſhall doo vs to wete.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf the Lordes common be ſo char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by anye tenaunte, with moo beaſtes then he ſhoulde after the quantitie of hys tenure, ye ſhall do vs to wete.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf there be any bondman of bloud that longeth to thys Lordeſhyp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is fled and dwelleth with out thys Lordeſhyp, without fine or raunſome makynge, ye ſhall do vs to wete.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf there be any alinacion ouer .xij. monethes and a daye, or leaſe for terme of yeres in fee, or fee tayle, ye ſhall do vs to wete.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf there be any tranſmutacion of poſſeſſion, that is to ſay, copy lande for fre lande, or free land for copy lande, wherof the lord might take any diſaduauntage in amending of the one, and paryng of the other, alſo of all maner of waſt done in howeſynge, lettinge downe or cuttynge the greate tymber, ye ſhal do vs to wete.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1841:3"/>Alſo of all treſpaſers, in corne, graſſe, or paſture, groues, or medowes, or fiſhers or foulers or hunters, or haukers, within this Lordeſhip or lordes warren, ye ſhal do vs to wete.</p>
            <p>Alſo if ther be any tenaunt of copy hold, tenaunt at wyll, or tenaunt of bond tenure, that ſuffer theyr tenauntes to be ruynous, and fall downe, or ells any fermer, bounden to reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, repayre not as he ought to do, do vs to wete.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf there be any bond man of bloud, within thys Lordſhyp, that purchaſeth anye fre lande, withoute leue or lycence, ye ſhall doo vs to wete, what he is, and what heire he hath.</p>
            <p>Alſo of all other thynges that ye haue knowen, that oughte to be preſented to the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des auayle, ye ſhal do vs to wete by the othes ye haue made, and bring in a true preſentment.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf any make any reſcus, or breake any reſt made by the baylyffe, or any other officer or elſe yf any man breake the lordes pounde, that is to ſay a dyſtreſſe put in the Lordes pounde by an offycer, and taken oute agayne wythoute ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf you know any that remoueth or pulleth vppe mere ſtones, or ſtakes betwene Lordeſhyppe, and Lordeſhyppe, or tenaunt, and tenaunte, whither it be bonde or free, preſente
<pb facs="tcp:1841:4"/>
theyr names.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf any tenaunte geue any lande to the Churche, that is to ſay, to mortmayne ſith the Statute thereof was made without lycence of the Quene, and the Lorde of thys Lordeſhyp, ye ſhall do vs to wete.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf any man haue incroched anye of the lordes ſoyle, that is to ſay, Land, medowe, more, paſture, or anye vacant ground without ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the lorde, preſent there names.</p>
            <p>Alſo if any man hold two tenemente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and waſteth the one, as yf he withdrewe anye trees from the one to the other, yf ye knowe anye ſuch preſent there names by your othe.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf anye tenaunte, haue made anye ſtrype or waſt vpon his bond teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nt, Stripe, that is to ſay, pulling of vp trees, or hedges, waſt is to ſaye, lettinge houſes to fall downe, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulte of reparacyons, yf there be anye ſuch, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente theym.</p>
            <p>Alſo, yf ye knowe anye tenaunte that wythdraweth or kepeth the euydence that lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to thys Lordeſhyppe, Courte Roules, Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, Cuſtomaryes, or anye other euydence pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente theym.</p>
            <p>Alſo, yf anye haue with theyr Cattell, for charged or ouerleyne anye common, within the precyncte of thys maner, or anye part or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
<pb facs="tcp:1841:4"/>
of the ſame, there are foure ſeueral commons, that is to ſaye, Commen Appendent, Common Appertenaunt, Common in Groſſe, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe de Viſinage: Yf any of you pretend to haue Common Appendent to ani part of your frehold and to comon vnder that nature of comon, then meaſured to a certayne nombre, that is, as many beaſtes, as the foder or profites of your corne rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vnto, ſuſtayne and fynde in wynter, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny maye you kepe in the common in ſommer, yf any of you haue alyenacion of frehold, where vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you pretende to haue thys common, your inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt paſſeth therwith. Anno xiiii. Hen. iiii. Fol. iii. Aſwel you may haue thys common in any water or other voyde place, whervppon maye ryſe anye commoditie, or other aduauntage, for a common welth, as turues, or otherwiſe incident or belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng to any part of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, as it appereth. Anno. xiiii. E. iiii. And this common ſerueth for beaſtes conueniable: And where any of you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to haue any Common Appertenaunt, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in Groſe, theſe commons dyffer that ther be not a meſurable, but that euery tenaunt maye at hys pleaſure put in his cattel, without admeſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and theſe commons ſerueth as wel for bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes conueniable as other, &amp; is moſt commonlye by preſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Percauſe de Viſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nage, is wheras two townes, or two manours are adioyning and haue vſed time out of mynde, to entre common with theyr cattell in the waſte feldes, or other groundes, next adioyning and is alſo by preſcription.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1841:5"/>Alſo yf the Lorde haue anye villan as bondemen or neyffes incident or belongynge to hys maner, ſo that any of them dwell or inhabite out of the precincte or lymyttes of thys hys ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, with that it be within the yeare and the daye, next or immediatelye after hys or theyr de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partyng, at the Lordes Baylyffe, or other offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, may receaſe him or them agayne to the lords vſe and behofe.</p>
            <p>Alſo, and yf any ſuch villayne haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited, or dwelled out of the precinct of this ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour, a hole yeare and a daye in anye frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chyſed towne, or other lybertie, that Lordes Baylyffes, can take no lawefull ſeaſure of hym duryng ſuch tyme as he abydeth in the ſame lybertie, but at hys nexte commyng to receaſe hym.</p>
            <p>Alſo yf anye vyllan there be inhabyted within thys maner or elles where, that without the aſſent of the Lord, hath marryed anye of hys daughters to any free man, ſo that by ſuch mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age the lordes inherytaunce is hindered or deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it is contrary to the ſtatute thereof made, or yf any vyllan hath put hys childe to ſcoole, or made hym a preyſt, there ought no villan ſo to do, with oute the aſſent of the Lorde.</p>
            <p>Alſo, &amp; yf any of the Lords villans ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be that ſence the laſt courte, haue purchaſed anye freholde, gyue it in knowledge that the Lordes officer, before any alienacion by the ſame vyllan,
<pb facs="tcp:1841:5"/>
made, maye take lawefull ſeaſure of it, to the vſe and behoue of the lord: Yf any alyenacion be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any clayme or other ſeaſure be made by the Lord, it ſhall bare the Lord for the ſeaſure after, but yf it be the Quenes caſe, <hi>Quia nullum tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pus occurris Regi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo of all theim that be harme doers in the Lordes woodes, ſprynges, hedges, rowes or otherwiſe within the manor, or thoſe that be harme doers in the Lordes general feldes, inclo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſures, medowes, paſtures, or in any other feldes, within the Lordeſhyppe.</p>
            <p>Alſo of all Dyches, Lanes, and bye wayes, that are not well and ſuffycyently repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſcoured, and amended, and al bowes, braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and other trees, that ouer lye and ouerhan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth anye of them, howe long they haue bene ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered where and in whole defaulte.</p>
            <p>Alſo of al thoſe that vſe and dayly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſtome to hunt, or hauke within this Lordſhip, to thentent to diſtroy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords warren, or other game within this maner, or they that vſe to take Feſauntes, Partryges, or Quales, with whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ingen it be, it is inquirable and fynable by the ſtatute, there ought no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to kepe any grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound, or hound, but if he may diſpend frely xl.<abbr>s.</abbr> 
               <hi>Per Annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo yf anye copyholder haue made
<pb facs="tcp:1841:6"/>
anye ſurrender out of thys courte, ſence the laſte lawe daye by whoſe handes it was made, and to what vſe, and preſente it.</p>
            <p>Alſo, of all theſe, and of all other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that you haue knowledge of, that oughte to be preſented in this court to the Lordes auayle, you ſhall goo together, and bryng in a true pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1841:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
